# **DIPESH JAIN**

IT Security Consultant

Email: ddipeshj@gmail.com, Mob: 9650990997

#### **SUMMARY**

16+ years of intensive work experience with prestigious Indian government / private organizations in different IT verticals such as IT Security, IT Network Administration, Data Centre Management, Framing of IT Policy, Conducting IS Audits, Statutory Compliances, Cloud Computing etc.

Also have exposure of ERP implementation (PeopleSoft and SAP), Software Development, Database Administration, IT Procurements, Contracts, Rolling plans, Annual budgets etc.

### **QUALIFICATIONS**

- Master of Technology in Computing Systems and Infrastructure from BITS Pilani(pursuing).
- Bachelor of Technology in Computer Science & Engineering with 71% (1<sup>st</sup> Division) in 2004 from U.P Technical University, Lucknow.
- Secured 87 % Marks in 12<sup>th</sup> Std with 93% in Comp. Sc.
- Secured 81 % Marks in 10<sup>th</sup> Std.

#### KEY ACCOMPLISHMENTS

- Received <u>Appreciation letter from CEO</u>, NSPCL for implementation of SAP / ERP in record time of nine and half months in NSPCL.
- Secured <u>99.02 %</u>, <u>AIR-262</u> in GATE (Computer Sc.) in year 2005.
- I received Certificate of Merit from CBSE for reasons of outstanding academic performance and for being among top 0.1 percent of the successful candidates of All India Secondary School Examination 1998 in Mathematics.

#### **WORK EXPERIENCE**

Period : 12.12.2018 – till date 11.12.2018

**Project**: A premier Govt Financial Organization (Name Confidential)

**Department**: Information Technology **Designation**: E6/ Chief Manager

### **JOB RESPONSIBILITIES**

### A. IT Security Operations

- 1. Administration of Security Devices & Services such as Firewall, Server-Security, Endpoint-Antivirus, Mail-Security, Proxy server etc.
- 2. Implementation of Anti-APT (Advanced Threat Protection) Appliances Trend Micro Deep Discovery Inspector (DDI) and Deep Discovery Analyser (DDAN)
- 3. Regular Monitoring of Events and alerts through Logs generated from Firewalls, Servers, Endpoints and getting resolutions from OEM and internal team to prevent security threats in real time. Discussions on Monthly MDR reports and taking actions proactively.
- 4. Antivirus Management, Patch updation, Intrusion prevention and detection through past logs and events, Configuration of Anti-Spam gateways and spam monitoring.
- 5. Restoration of Servers, Applications and Database from Backup after Security Incident in the organization.
- 6. Successfully conducted IT Awareness Training for all employees and contract staff of the organization.

#### B. IT Policy

Framing of IT Policies, IT Policy Implementation, in areas listed below:

1. IT Governance framework

- 2. Acceptable use policy
- 3. IT Password policy
- 4. Portable media policy
- 5. Physical and environmental security policy
- 6. IT Hardware / Software maintenance & replacement policy
- 7. Software development / maintenance policy
- 8. IT Outsourcing policy
- 9. IT Audit policy
- 10. Access Control policy
- 11. Digital Information classification and handling policy
- 12. Backup and Restoration policy
- 13. IT Cyber Security policy
- 14. Business Continuity policy
- 15. Incident Management policy
- 16. IT Remote Work policy

### C. IT Audits

- 1. Scoping of IT Security audit as per industry standards.
- 2. Conducted IS Audit of the organization's IT Applications and ICT Infrastructure.

## D. Disaster recovery Site on Cloud

- 1. **Disaster Recovery:** Continuous replication of data from DR to DRC, Online backups through Sybase Client, Offline backups through Tape Library Management (HP), DC-DR Mock drills, Optimal network configuration and DNS Management for seamless DC-DR swap with least downtime.
- 2. **Cloud Hosting:** Hosting and Management of software applications like SRM portal, ESS portal, THE ORGANIZATION Website, etc. on Cloud with DNS Zone Management, NATing, cPanel, etc.

## E. IT Network Operations

- 1. Administration of Routers, Core Switches and Access Switches etc. with proper configuration of VLAN, Policies, Routing, QOS, Authentication etc.
- 2. Providing Remote access connectivity through Internet for outside users through SSL VPN for Work from Home requirements.
- 3. Administration of Floor level Switches, I/O points, Field cables, Patch cables, Endpoint LAN Adapters and ports.
- 4. Provisioning of Internet to employees and casual staff based on authorization and deploying restrictions, Proxy server Administration etc."

**Period** : 01.11.2013 – 11.12.2018

**Project** : NSPCL (NTPC- SAIL Joint Venture Company)

**Department**: IT/ERP/Communication **Designation**: E5/Manager, NTPC Ltd

#### JOB RESPONSIBILITIES

#### A. IT Network Administration and IT Security

- WAN Connectivity: Designing of NSPCL's Wide Area Networks to cater both NSPCL and NTPC
  networks, Grouping and Isolation of MPLS links through BGP protocols to avoid overlapping of
  networks, Configuration of routers with static routing, QOS, Port aggregation, Ensuring
  availability of WAN Connectivity (primary and secondary) at all sites with regular monitoring
  through different network tools (PRTG).
- 2. **Network Security:** Centralised Firewall Management for all NSPCL locations, configuration of hosts, host groups, routing, access control policies, routing, web filtering etc. (Fortinet-600c & Cyberoam-CR1000ING-XP).

- 3. **Endpoint Security:** Antivirus Management, Patch updation, Intrusion prevention and detection through past logs and events, Configuration of Anti-Spam gateways and spam monitoring.
- 4. **Secure Connectivity through SSL**: Configuration of SSL digital server certificates on servers to provide their secure https access to NSPCL users over internet, Configuration of SSL VPN for connecting users to critical applications over internet with security controls based on authenticated user logins, IP address, MAC address, limited time-based slots etc.

### **B.** Server Administration

- 1. Planning, Procurement, Installation, Commissioning, Maintenance, Administration and Monitoring of Unix servers, Windows Blade Servers, Virtual Machines hosted on these physical servers. Planning of BOQ as per SAPS recommended by SAP. Augmentation of Servers before reaching utilisation limit.
- 2. Installation, Configuration and Updation of Windows Server 2008 / 2012, Linux-Ubuntu-14.x / 16.x, UNIX HP-UX.

### C. Storage and Backup Administration:

1. Planning, Procurement, Installation, Commissioning, Maintenance, Administration and Monitoring of SAN / NAS Storage Augmentation of Storage before reaching utilisation limit. Configuration of logical drives and assignment of SAN Storage (HP 3PAR) pools to different Servers.

#### D. IT Data Centre Management

- 1. **IT and ERP Infrastructure**: Planning, Procurement, Installation, Commissioning, Maintenance, Administration and Monitoring of critical equipment installed at Data Centre (DC) and Disaster Recovery Centre (DRC). These equipment include High end Unix servers, Windows Blade Servers, Virtual Machines hosted on these physical servers. Planning of BOQ as per SAPS recommended by SAP. Augmentation of Servers and Storage before reaching utilisation limit.
- 2. **Capacity Planning:** Making 3-Year IT Rolling Plans, Annual Budgets and Annual Utilisation as per IT requirements of NSPCL.
- 3. **Data Centre Management:** Rack wise Power usage planning and monitoring, Environment monitoring in respect of ambient temperature and clean air. Ensuring time synchronisation of all devices through master GPS clock, Round the clock staff deployment with authenticated access to server room.

Period : 20.04.2010 - 31.10.2013

**Project**: Faridabad Gas Power Station, NTPC Ltd.

**Department**: IT/ERP/Communication **Designation**: E3/Dy. Manager, NTPC Ltd

## **JOB RESPONSIBILITIES**

#### A. IT Infrastructure Administration

- 1. Administration and Maintenance of Servers Windows and Linux based
- 2. Maintenance and Support for Desktops, Printers and Peripherals.

## **B.** Network Administration

- 1. **LAN Connectivity:** Network Design Layout according to Class of Networks, Configuration of L3 switches with VLAN.
- 2. **Providing Internet Facility** through Internet Lease Lines with web filtering and web traffic usage monitoring through proxy server.

Period : 06.09.2004 - 19.04.2010

**Project**: Corporate Centre – NTPC Ltd., Scope Complex, New Delhi

**Department**: HR-IT

**Designation**: E2/Engineer, NTPC Ltd

### JOB RESPONSIBILITIES

- 1. **Unix / Linux System Administration:** Installation / Configuration and Administration of HP-Unix / Linux operating systems.
- 2. **Database Administration:** Installation / Configuration and Administration of Oracle 9i /10g DBMS with data backups and migration to other DBMS.

## **PERSONAL DETAILS**

Father's Name: Anil Kumar Jain

Birth year : 1982 Marital Status : Married Gender : Male

**Hobbies** : Photography, Socializing, Listening Music.

**Location** : Noida/Delhi

## **DECLARATION**

I hereby declare that the above written particulars are true to the best of my knowledge & belief.

**Dipesh Jain**